BASED ON THE ÅRE MURDERS:
HIDDEN IN SHADOWS
BY VIVECA STEN
Mom!
THE ÅRE MURDERS
HIDDEN IN SHADOWS
PART 1
Good morning, sunshine.
I would've driven all the way,
but some idiot's blocking the way.
Here you go.
Coffee…
Cool, or…
Okay.
What's up?
Just that a body shows up
the day before you go on parental leave.
Do you know
what Bruce Lee's favorite drink was?
No.
Watah!
-Go!
-Okay.
POLICE LINE - DO NOT CROSS
When's Ylva coming?
In two or three hours.
We've found
a left leg over there
and a right hand, I think,
over by the bridge.
It's called the suicide bridge.
Hi, this is Johan.
I can't take your call right--
We still haven't found
the left forearm or the right leg.
It's a male, that much we can establish,
but we haven't been able
to establish his identity.
Someone mentioned suicide, but…
If the person was alive
when the body was torn apart
and the head landed in the snow,
there should be,
well, livor mortis on his right cheek,
from resting against the ground.
However, livor mortis
is present on the neck,
which may suggest
that the person was already dead
when the body was torn apart
in the train collision.
There's a blunt impact injury to the head
I'd like to take a look at…
Sorry, I'll just…
Impact, like from a blow?
I don't know.
To establish that,
I need to examine the remains
back at the lab.
Look.
The clothes and the body
are covered in these.
Red cotton fibers.
Here.
Thank you.
I'm heading home.
Yeah, I'll stay. I need a few minutes.
I understand.
You're not going to Bygget?
No, I don't think so.
-See you.
-See you tomorrow.
Fucking pig!
-Hi.
Hi!
It's so nice to see you! Join us inside!
-It's so crowded.
-Yeah, but it'll be so fun!
-I'm really not up for it.
-Join us.
I'm going home.
Okay, I get it.
-What?
-You want to dance, so let's dance.
-No, I'm heading out.
-Out?
-Yes.
-For a smoke?
-What?
-I'm going to smoke. Come.
Come on.
You want to swing by?
-Let me just…
-No, it's the last one.
No, sorry.
This is the police. How may I help?
Hi. It's probably nothing…
I just…
My husband hasn't been home all day, and…
And I can't reach him on his phone.
You wake up happy.
Let's say goodbye to Mommy.
Good morning, Mommy.
-Oh my! Hi!
-I'm awake.
There.
Hello, sweetie!
-God, I'm going to miss her.
-She won't even know you've been away.
-No.
-Okay, go.
-You're messing up our routine.
-Which is?
The morning news, black coffee,
dinner ideas from Steffo…
Then I'm going to eat these thighs…
-Can you take her?
-I don't have time.
-Real quick.
Do you want to come to Mommy?
Then Mommy's leaving.
Should I take you in my bag?
-Hi.
-The remains belong to Johan Andersson.
Former ski star and partner of J&L Event.
-Resident of Duved.
-Oh.
-Is it him? I saw him win World Cup races.
-Yeah, his…
His wife reported him missing last night.
Has she been informed?
I want you and Hanna to take it.
And Daniel, the cause of death
was a heavy blow to the head
with a blunt or flat object.
He can't have fallen on the track?
It's unlikely.
The injury is too high up.
So it's murder.
So it would seem.
I'm sorry, but we need you.
Can you postpone your parental leave?
I don't think Hanna
should do this on her own right now.
No, of course not.
-Thank you, Daniel. See you later.
-Okay.
Johan?
God… We worked together at Ski Hill.
Damn, that's sad.
-Who the hell would want to murder him?
-Grip wants me to lead the investigation.
Well, that's not possible.
-You're on parental leave this week.
-I know that.
No.
What can I do?
Ida, Grip needs me.
Listen, this training is really important
for my career.
I know,
but you can take the course next year.
So I'm supposed to unpack my bag
and stay home with Alice?
What can I do? You can't put
a murder investigation on hold.
No, but you can put my life on hold.
I barely saw you
during the last murder investigation.
I stayed home with Alice who had colic,
so I think it's your turn.
-I know. I'm sorry.
-Just figure it out.
Hi, sweetie.
Hi!
Kisses.
I love you.
Bye.
-Okay. Bye, honey.
-Bye.
She's pooped, so change her.
-Do it right away.
-Yeah.
Bye.
-Hey.
Ida's out of town, but…
-It'll be fine.
-I can take Anton instead.
-No, it's fine.
-It's not a problem.
-I'll go by the book--
-It's fine.
Or I can take Anton,
and you can grab a coffee.
Okay. Did someone wake up
on the wrong side of the bed?
Wake up? I haven't even slept.
Okay.
Sure.
Sorry.
No worries.
Hanna Ahlander, Åre PD.
This is my colleague, Daniel Lindskog.
-Hi.
Have you found him?
Yes.
Okay… What happened?
Maybe we should go inside.
He's dead.
I'm sorry.
Our condolences.
I don't know what to say. I'm sorry.
We're not skiing off-piste
with Johan Andersson?
I don't know where the hell he is,
but it's been a nice day.
-You can't do this at home.
-No, but…
Excuse me.
J&L Event, Linus Sundin.
-Rafael Herrera, Åre PD.
-We expect a full refund!
I'm out with clients. What is it?
-It's about your colleague.
-What?
Your colleague, Johan Andersson,
has been found dead.
When can we talk to you?
-Hi.
-Are you Leo's dad?
-He's Leo's biological dad.
-Jens.
-Daniel.
Leo.
Do you remember the last time
you saw Johan?
-I told you that…
-We had breakfast together.
Okay.
Then you went to a concert in…
in Östersund?
You and your mom?
Do you remember what time?
The concert started
at 7:00
with an opening act.
Okay.
And what did you do after?
We slept at the hotel.
Then we left early,
the day after.
Johan wasn't at home when we got back.
But sometimes he sleeps at his office.
He had a…
a dinner that night,
with a childhood friend.
Carl Willner.
How long ago was it
that you separated from Marion?
Well, 12 or 13 years ago.
How was your relationship with Johan?
I mean, he's been really good for Leo,
so I'm very grateful for that.
Leo.
Will you catch whoever did it?
We will.
We'll do our best.
Let's go home.
Listen.
-Call us anytime.
-Okay. Thank you.
Johan was having dinner
with a childhood friend the night he died.
Carl Willner.
Yeah.
I have to stop by Ida's mom's.
She went for a walk with Alice
and locked herself out.
I'll just take Anton.
Tips are pouring in.
-Really?
-Yes.
"Last night,
I heard loud noises from underground."
"I saw the murderer in my dreams."
-You're cheery today.
-Some people…
Here's a dog owner
who saw a dark van with a broken taillight
on the dirt road
between the train station and the bridge.
That could be something.
Yeah.
Hi. Carl Willner?
Yeah, he's over there.
We just need a minute.
-Hi.
Hanna Ahlander, Åre PD.
-Carl. Hi.
-My colleague, Anton Lundgren.
-Hi.
Oh, do you know each other?
-Well…
-No.
No, we've never met.
Right.
Well, you've heard what happened to Johan.
Yes.
Marion said that…
Are you sure that…
It can't have been an accident?
No, we're treating it as a crime.
Damn.
Johan was here. He…
It was strange, actually.
He showed up with a bloody nose.
He stopped the bleeding with a shirt, but…
He seemed very stressed
and left almost immediately.
-And the shirt? What did he do with it?
-He threw it in the dumpster out back.
He said he'd fallen.
Why did he come here?
We were supposed to have dinner. He…
Well, we do it every week.
But he just stopped by to cancel.
Fuck.
You said he stopped by.
Where was he going?
He said he was going out of town.
Where to?
I don't know.
I assumed it was work-related,
but now it sounds strange.
-When was he leaving?
-Later that night.
-Is this the shirt?
-Yes, exactly.
Let's book it.
Okay.
The deceased has been identified
as downhill skier Johan Andersson.
Next of kin have been notified,
and the police is invest--
Hello?
We've had a board meeting
and decided not to renew the lease.
What the hell? We had a deal.
The board have made its decision.
Are you kidding me?
Cunt!
You fucking Jesus freaks.
You're going to regret this.
The same day as my partner…
Linus, it's our land.
The congregation has every right to…
-But you promised to renew the lease.
-Things have changed.
-Johan's dead.
-Hey, you fucking cunt!
STAFF CARE
HAVE A NICE WEEKEND
I'm coming, honey!
-Hello?
-It's an emergency.
Hi.
Thank you. Come in.
I'm coming.
She's finally asleep. Sit down.
-Do you want a drink?
-No, thank you.
No, okay. Hey, sorry for the mess.
-I haven't had time to clean.
-Don't worry.
I'll just tidy up a bit.
I was thinking about…
I saw that this event agency had…
I looked at their Insta
and saw they had posted a picture.
The guy next to Johan has a shirt
just like the bloody one Anton found.
That's Johan's partner, Linus Sundin.
We're interviewing him tomorrow.
Well done, Hanna.
I'm glad you're here in Åre.
Raffe went through J&L Event's books.
Apparently, they've applied for a loan.
We don't know
if Johan or Linus made the application.
Both had signatory authority.
But what I wanted to show you…
Hold on.
My head's been killing me.
I haven't been able to sleep.
I thought it was a tumor,
but Ida made me go to the optician.
It turns out I need glasses.
But I haven't received them yet.
How much money are we talking about?
Half a million.
I wonder if the company, or one of them,
had financial problems, but…
Yeah.
Should we…
continue tomorrow?
-Yes.
-Now that Alice is asleep, I should also…
Yeah, of course. Yes.
Thank you for the formula.
-You saved me.
-No worries.
-Hi.
I take it you've heard.
Well, how's Leo coping?
I can't believe it.
Do the police know
what could have happened?
I don't know.
Nothing?
Hey, you need to clean out the garage.
You can't keep your liquor there.
The police will snoop everywhere.
Everything has to be gone by tomorrow.
-Okay?
-Okay.
Our thoughts today
are with Johan Andersson and his family.
Some of us knew him personally.
He was well-known and appreciated
in our village.
Such a reminder of our mortality
can give rise to fear.
But it can also pave the way for
forgiveness and reconciliation.
MISSED CALL
CARL
CAN WE MEET?
-Hi.
-Hey.
I just wanted to come here
to tell you in person that I'm…
Well, I'm a cop.
Well, I guess you noticed that, but…
Since you're a witness
in a murder investigation,
you and I can't…
We can't see each other anymore.
You haven't come out yet, huh?
Well, it's a bit complicated.
Hey… Man, sorry if I…
I get it.
It sucks, but I get it.
So I'm just going to cancel your booking.
You'll get the booking fee back as well.
Thank you. Bye.
-Hi.
-Hi. Hanna Ahlander, Åre PD.
I heard you have questions.
Yes, exactly.
But I'd like to take a look
at Johan's office first.
Yeah, should we…
TUESDAY 20TH
PILGRIMSFJÄLL
TUESDAY 27TH
What's Pilgrimsfjäll?
Pilgrimsfjäll?
I don't know.
I don't know what it is, but…
-Do you know what might have happened?
-We don't know.
Do you recognize this?
Johan used it to stop a bleeding.
He must have borrowed it.
It's been here in the office.
What happened to your lip?
Sorry, can we do this over the phone?
-I…
-We're almost done.
-I have pick up my son.
-It'll be quick. We're almost done.
The lip?
We were going to make an investment,
build a high ropes course, and…
The same day it happened,
I had discovered that Johan
hadn't signed on for the loan, so…
We were at the office.
I confronted him about it.
He had suddenly changed his mind.
And we started arguing.
Who threw the first punch?
He did.
I just defended myself.
MOTHER-IN-LAW
Where were you later? In the evening?
I watched my son's hockey practice.
Then I went home and…
Jens and I…
-We sat and…
-Jens Wernolf?
-Leo's dad?
-Yes, exactly.
He's renting my guest cabin
until he finds his own place.
We watched soccer until half past eleven.
Then I went to bed.
I have to take this.
What made Johan change his mind?
I have no idea.
You don't know?
No.
-But you knew him well?
-Yes, but he refused to tell me why.
It's got to do
with the congregation we're leasing from.
Their pastor, Ole Nordhammar…
Johan didn't like him. I don't know why.
Okay.
Listen.
I've known Johan all my life.
He was like a brother to me.
I loved him.
I would never…
Okay.
Don't leave town
until we've verified your alibi.
Sure.
-Didn't you get my text?
-No.
-Well, I don't want any more.
-What?
The police were here.
They could come back anytime.
Absolutely not.
I placed an order for two months.
All right,
then I'll have to cut your throat
and kill you.
I'm only joking.
-Well, this is the last one.
-Sure.
-Has she been good?
-Yes, like an angel.
-But she might be hungry.
-Okay, thank you.
Bye.
…Raffe
Cumpleaños feliz
What do you wish for?
A raise.
Congratulations.
-Congrats.
-Wow.
-Finally 60.
-Thank you.
Thank you, Anton.
But… PiscoLogía!
Wow, thanks so much. From?
-From all of us.
-From all of you. Thanks so much.
We understand English.
I promised the boys to go night skiing.
Go sit down.
Give me ten minutes.
He used to wear a wedding ring.
Where is it?
It was found like that,
with a glove on, without a ring.
-It was found like that.
-Why take off your wedding ring?
Well, if you're fighting,
seeing someone else, going to Bygget…
What do I know?
Okay, Hanna. Tomorrow we'll visit
the pastor that Linus mentioned.
-Raffe, have you confirmed Linus' alibi?
-No.
Jens Wernolf isn't returning my calls.
I'll go to his place tomorrow.
Good.
There, there. Okay, let's…
I have to change her.
I also have to go.
The slope is closing soon.
-Hi.
-Hey.
We're from the police.
We'd like to ask you a few questions.
Hanna. Daniel.
May we come in?
Yeah, sure.
I'm cooking for my wife.
She's bedridden.
No, wait a minute.
Can you eat fish while pregnant?
As long as it's farmed.
This is perch that I caught in Åresjön.
Then I wouldn't advise it.
Yeah.
We're having a baby. Our first.
Congratulations.
Thanks.
I thought you might get in touch.
What with Johan's murder and…
Tell me about your relationship
with Johan.
Well, his company was leasing land
from the church for a high ropes course.
There were discussions
on whether to renew the contract or not.
Was Johan upset about it?
Well, it's possible.
But while he was alive,
a majority of the board members
wanted to renew the lease.
Johan was reliable.
Pilgrimsfjäll?
Yeah.
What's that?
It's a folk high school for Bible studies.
But it's just
at the planning stage for now.
Was Johan involved?
No.
Hi.
Hi, honey.
What are you doing up?
I was just going to the bathroom.
-The doctor said it was okay.
-Yes, of course.
They're from the police.
They're wondering about the congregation's
dealings with J&L Event.
-Hanna.
-Rebecka.
Yes.
Right. This is my colleague, Daniel.
Yeah.
Remember what the doctor said.
-Not too long.
-No.
I'll be up with some food.
Thank you.
So, any more questions,
or would you like some fish?
No, thank you.
I think we're…
We're done. We'll be in touch
if we have more questions.
Okay.
He's lying.
"Pilgrimsfjäll" was written
all over Johan's calendar.
It doesn't mean he's lying.
He might not know about it.
It was weird.
-When she came down?
-Yeah.
Raffe says that Linus' alibi checks out.
What are you looking at?
Östersund has mapped out
where Johan's car was
the weeks prior to his death.
Okay?
What's between Tjärntorpet
and the Fröå mine?
It's a large area of woodland,
close to where we were just now.
Why?
Johan was there two or three times a week.
And time and date correlate
with "Pilgrimsfjäll" in his calendar.
I think his dealings with Ole
went beyond just the land lease.
Okay, I have to take over from Ida's mom.
Shouldn't you take a break?
No.
No, okay. See you tomorrow.
Sure.
Show me.
I've told you to stay in your room.
Don't ever undermine me again.
You have reached your destination.
What are you doing up?
You should be resting.
Nothing.
Hi.
What's that?
Just some clothes I'm giving away.
I mean, soon they won't fit me.
Right.
Why are you lying to me?
I'm not.
Hi.
Now's actually not a great time.
Whose skis are those?
They're my wife's.
-I don't ski. I just fall down.
-Right.
-I'd like to talk to her.
-Well…
My wife's going through
a high-risk pregnancy.
She really needs her rest.
Doctor's orders.
Yeah…
Or…
What did you want?
To check if you're okay.
Why wouldn't we be?
Either I call for backup or you let me in.
The police want to talk to you.
-Hi, Rebecka.
-Hi.
I'd like to talk to you. Is it okay?
You can wait outside.
Go ahead.
Did I interrupt anything?
No.
Pretty.
Thank you.
It's… kind of like a rosary.
To remind me of God in everyday life.
Like a lifeline.
How are you?
If you want to,
you and I will leave here now.
Do you want that?
-Yes.
-Okay.
Then let's do that.
It'll be okay.
My colleague will come
to get your version of it.
-Hi.
-Hi. Welcome.
Thank you.
I called you, or someone here,
maybe two hours ago.
-Yeah, right.
-Yes, exactly.
Hi, Anna. Sorry I haven't called.
-Hi.
-I was…
It's me.
Come home.
I love you.
Hey, don't talk to the police.
I've explained
it was all a misunderstanding.
I promise,
everything's going to be different now.
Where are you?
Granen Hotel, what can I do for you?
Don't call me again.
Thank you.
You knew Johan Andersson, right?
Yes.
May I sit down?
You were a couple, right?
How did you meet?
We met while I was working
on the development of
Pilgrimsfjäll, which is
a folk high school for Bible studies.
And I thought that J&L Events…
Maybe they could help us
with our nature experiences.
And then one thing
led to another.
I loved him…
very much.
I skied to our meeting place
so that Ole wouldn't suspect anything.
But did… Johan know
how Ole treated you?
What he had done?
Were you and Johan going on a trip?
Or you were going…
Yes, that evening.
When Johan found out I was pregnant,
he wanted to get me away from Ole.
But…
But he didn't come to the meeting place,
and he didn't answer his phone.
And then I found out…
Where was Ole
the night Johan was murdered?
I don't know.
I'll let you rest. Take it easy.
We'll bring you in the station tomorrow
and talk there.
Try to stay here in the room.
-Okay?
-Okay.
-Thank you.
-Yeah.
Hi. We have to bring in Ole.
Hold on, we just talked to him.
Yes, I know.
But he could be the one who killed Johan.
I'll pick you up.
It looks pretty dark.
Police! Open up!
Hey, Rebecka Nordhammar.
What's her room number?
We can't share any information
about our guests.
She's my wife.
Sorry, it's not possible.
No one's home.
Alain!
Check the back.
-No one's home.
-Okay.
-You stay here.
-Yeah.
She's not picking up.
Call the hotel.
Please. Open the door.
Hey.
I just want to talk.
I love you.
Can you just leave?
If you open the door,
we can talk, and I will explain--
I won't open.
I understand.
What I've done is unforgivable.
I want you to know that I'm sorry.
I'm so terribly sorry.
Hey.
I'll get help.
I'll call tomorrow, and I'll…
This is not the kind of father
I want to be.
I love you.
And I want us to be a family.
It's not your child.
Leave.
Subtitle translation by:
Josephine Roos Henriksson